How do you scale the reviewing process?
Because now that is blocking your senior
engineers. It burns them out. One answer
is don't do any code reviews at all.
>> This is Florian Butau, AI engineer at
Xavier, and we discuss the biggest
bottleneck in software engineering right
now, code reviews. [music]
What do you think of Spectre and
development? Which of these guardrails
gave you the most value? Does it matter
which harness I use, GitHub Copilot,
Cloud Code, Codex? [music]
>> It matters immensely. Basically, what
employees are doing is they they give
people a hand grenade, which is AI,
[music] and then say don't blow up the
hand grenade, but use it.
>> This is how the best engineers are
solving the code review bottleneck right
now.
Here's the full episode.
>> [music]
>> As we generate more code, this is really
in the build phase, code reviewing
becomes a bottleneck.
I've just come back from Google I/O,
that was last week. I think when this
episode comes out, a couple weeks ago.
And even there, Google and the people
there acknowledge, yeah, code review is
a bottleneck, and we don't know how to
solve it yet.
>> Yeah, Google's an interesting case
because um in 2025, they already
reported that 50% of their code is AI
generated, and then they're pushing for
75%.
Um
I always like to look at the big players
to see what they do because on one side,
you see all of these crazy numbers, like
efficiency gains, um or
we automated our entire deployment layer
with AI, like Spotify did, for example.
But very seldom do you actually see how
they do that, right? So, they report all
of these gains,
but then how do you translate that to
your own work?
And that part is often missing.
And um for the big companies, I think um
so, if you if you look a little bit
about how um you know, what they publish
and what they write,
you can kind of see that they they have
like a
an approach that
prioritizes reviewing now more, like it
becomes more standardized
because they've identified that um now
that you can generate code very cheaply,
you know, um the bottleneck is moving
somewhere else. Now, some people and
this is another thing, but some people
would argue that
writing code was never the bottleneck.
Depends on kind of, you know, how do you
see software engineering?
But truth of the matter is you generate
10x more code. So, now you have more
pressure on your reviewing. On your
engineers, etc.
And I think what the big companies are
doing right now is they are combating
that with
policies on reviews.
At Amazon for example, there have been
some instances where there were outages,
revenue loss. Due to your AI AI
generated code and then they put in
policies in place where they now require
some parts of the code or
some parts of the systems that they have
to be reviewed by senior engineers
before anything gets merged or deployed.
So, they are identifying that, you know,
for in some cases AI generated code has
to be scrutinized
um well
stronger than in other cases.
So, you can see that and at the same
time you see other companies who say,
"Okay, we automated our entire PR review
process." They're playing like these um
How would you say? Well, I like to think
about it as a little bit like
there's a horizontal way of scaling AI
engineering and a vertical one.
>> Okay.
>> The horizontal one is where you automate
like processes you currently have like a
PR review. Like you can you can say any
PR that is created automatically
reviewed with Copilot for example.
And that's what a lot of companies do.
But then they don't really talk about
how that improves the quality.
Right? So, they're automating part of
the human pipeline that we have.
>> What's then the vertical axis?
>> The vertical axis is
if you have um
a project and a small specialized team
um you let them build their own tooling
to make sure that the product ships
and um is developed in the way that they
intend to.
>> Mhm.
>> So, they are more involved in building
custom-built um environments for their
coding agents and for the team to
deliver the software.
Like they don't have a blueprint that
applies
to the product automatically. They
refine it.
>> Yeah. And this is the
I see us stacking a lot of capabilities,
right? We have the model on one hand,
and then the agent
kind of harness around the model
specifically, and you're talking about
an environment in which this agent
harness operates. Or how should I view
that?
>> Well, maybe maybe we should
just go back one step. Um
So, if you look at software engineering,
um
I think it's a well-established process
by now, like if we think before the area
of AI.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh software development life cycle,
everybody knows it. Um
And
part of Well, the review was done by
humans, and it would work because code
wasn't delivered faster than you could
review it. That has changed now with AI.
And so, the question now becomes, well,
how do you scale the reviewing process?
Right? Because now that is blocking your
senior engineers. It burns them out. Um
there studies about that where, you
know, cognitive death is growing, but
people don't understand or their own
code base
because they just don't have the time to
look at everything, or they don't even
want to look at the AI-generated code,
etc.
And so, the the question is, how do you
mitigate that?
>> Mhm.
>> And um one answer is, don't do any code
reviews at all. Okay, but then the next
question is, how do you do that?
So, I think
one way to do it is to engineer the
environment in which the agents operate
uh
with um
Well,
with intention, so that you don't have
to be the human in the loop to give the
agent feedback on common things.
>> Mhm.
>> And it starts with very simple things.
So, um like I'll just let's say code
formatting, automatic code formatter. We
already had that. Or a security check,
you know, lots of team has integrated
tools like SonarQube or something that
gives you feedback
uh that then a human would take and uh
fix the code with like with the feedback
from those systems.
Agents can do that automatically. So, if
you provide agents feedback on what
they're doing wrong
and hopefully as close as possible to
where the agent actually generates the
code
which [clears throat] means on the
developer's laptop, not necessarily in
GitHub
after you made your commit or your PR.
Then you are suddenly in this world of
where you're trying to engineer feedback
to the agents in a way that helps the
agents to run for a long time without
human intervention.
So, that's what I mean by building these
types of environments.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think it's very easy to get
started with it.
A lot of it will feel like
but we've been doing this before.
But now you're giving the agent that
feedback. You're not taking it as a
human anymore.
Right?
And
some of the models are surprisingly good
at self-correcting themselves once you
pinpoint them what they did wrong.
And let the environment give them that
feedback.
>> Yeah. Does the harness in this equation
does it matter which harness I use?
GitHub Copilot, Cloud Code, CodeX?
>> Oh yeah, absolutely.
Well, in my experience the harness
matters more than the model.
>> Okay.
>> I mean the harness is what provides the
tools, what provides
some type of prompting,
provides the memory layer, and all of
these things
that then get submitted to the LLM to
generate a response for example where
the LLM, you know, wants
to make a tool call, etc. And the
harness provides them the capability to
execute the tool call for the LLM.
It matters immensely.
I made an experiment in one of my
projects where I tried to
implement a tool based on specifications
and tests. So, I had a full suite of
specifications like specification-driven
development like many people like to do
nowadays. They The idea is that
if you specify your product exactly
enough, the AI will be able to implement
it. The exactly according to
specifications,
which is unfortunately not true. Uh but
it's an attempt that I made and that
failed. And then I thought, okay, what
if I
uh use the TDD idea and just generate me
all of the behavioral tests up front.
And then let that be the feedback to the
agent who tries to follow my
specifications.
And depending on the harness that I
used, it worked or didn't work even if I
was using the top frontier model in both
harnesses.
>> Okay. Which which harness gave you the
best results?
>> Well, that keeps changing all the time.
So
>> [laughter]
>> um at that time it was a Claude code.
Um now I would have said I would say it
that shifted to Codex for implementation
work. Um but that's one of those things.
That's like a moving target, which is
also one of the reasons why you can't
really stop experimenting. There's this
tendency for software engineers to try
to um
systematize things and make it a process
and okay, this those are now the rules.
I don't think that works. Things are
>> still moving too quickly.
>> Um
Okay, maybe I should walk that back a
little bit. It works at some level, but
if you define in your policy we must
only use Claude code.
Um who knows what will happen when the
next release comes out.
>> Yeah.
>> It might behave completely different,
because the models have different
personalities.
Like some are very good at instruction
following, others are very good at
filling in the gaps if you don't provide
enough context as a human. So you need
to be careful uh which model you use as
well.
>> Yeah. I want to zoom in on kind of what
you recommend for harnesses, but before
we do
kind of following your train of thought
of spectrum development and solving kind
of the the code review process in that
way, you mentioned the TDD approach
worked better than the spectrum
development approach with a model
following instructions in that way.
>> Well, I would say well, spectrum was my
first attempt and that didn't go well.
It was a typical okay, I create the
perfect prompt
and then the model does something
different I didn't intend.
But when you give those the feedback in
addition to tell the model when it's off
track,
that worked for me in that particular
instance.
>> Mhm.
>> Um and I would say, you know, those
results might be transferable to other
project, but it really depends on the
project, which again brings us back to
the quest to the to the need to be uh to
be willing to experiment what works.
>> Yeah. And this feedback, just so I
understand, this is in an automated way,
right? So you have specs, then you have
execution, and it the feedback is not
you telling what it did wrong, but what
does that feedback cycle look like?
>> Uh exactly, yeah. So um in if when
you're using like these CLI tools, um
you have the ability to uh define
what is called, for example, a stop
hook. So when the agent is done with its
work,
>> Yeah.
>> the harness triggers uh an event, which
is a stop hook. And uh you can wire that
up to a shell script that you run, for
example. So you can automate running
your test suite or your guide rails. Uh
I like to call them guide rails.
And um
they then and you need to engineer your
guide rails so they actually output like
natural language text. This is
forbidden, do it in this and that way.
So you base the feedback encodes the
prompt that you would write as a human.
>> Mhm.
>> So then you trigger that, and then that
triggers uh the LLM to continue um
working on the thing. And you can pair,
you know, these feedbacks that you give
with um things like Ralph loop, um
you know, Codex and Claude, they now
have the goal um command, which really
helps.
So they will just keep running for long
and long until they fix the issue.
>> Yeah. So Ralph loops specifically allow
you to run whatever you want to do in a
loop, right? So it goes over it, and
this feedback mechanism would then be
input in an iteration to get it right
and to correct it. Goal is something
similar?
>> Uh the idea is the same.
>> The idea is the same.
>> Yeah. Um I don't know exactly what the
implementation of goal looks like, but
it seems to be functionally equivalent
to a Ralph loop.
>> And which of these guardrails that
you've put in place gave you the most
value? You mentioned linting already
some security controls. Do you have more
examples?
>> Um yeah, so I'm I'm I didn't know
before, but I've since become a great
fan of semantic grep.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh because it allows you to um put uh
regexes for things that it could catch
in code. For example, certain type of
code construct.
Um the example that I always give is um
I don't want any default values in any
of my methods in Python, for example.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, you can set default values um
for parameters in Python methods. And in
the signature of the method. And um
this, in my experience, is one of the
greatest sources of frustration
when you have to review and debug the
code later. So, I just
prevent that by putting a rule that
detects these uh code patterns.
And that then triggers um error. Um you
you must not write it in that way. It's
against policy.
>> Mhm.
>> Um so, semantic grep is really flexible
and
whenever I uh interrogate the AI um
about the code that it wrote, instead of
reviewing the code myself, you know,
some of these issues come up. You know,
why did you do it that way? It doesn't
make any sense.
That immediately triggers me, okay,
let's add another guardrail rule for
this particular uh type of pattern.
So, what then happens
over time is you're you're shaping your
environment, you're iterating towards it
to be tighter and tighter to be aligned
with your uh preferences as a human or
how you think code should look like.
And part of that is not only taste, um
but also
you want to enforce that the AI
generates code that is easy to
understand not for humans, even if you
don't want to read it as a human, but
also for AI.
Right? Code is context. So, that's why
code quality matters.
Uh if you just write code something, uh
sooner or later the AI is going to
confuse itself
>> Yeah.
>> by the code.
>> The sustainability of codebases has
always been needs to be simple and easy
to change.
>> Yes.
>> And that that perspective hasn't changed
with agents. We allow ourselves to
generate more code in the code that is
out there might not be simple and might
not be as easy to change, but we're
like, well, it works, right? And then
building on top of that
might be quite brittle.
>> Yes, and well, as humans we also allow
ourselves this little exception where
say as long as it's modular, it doesn't
matter if one of the modules is messy or
something as long as it's isolated,
right?
>> Behind abstractions.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's also something that I found
with AI. If you keep your things
modular,
that helps a lot. Like if you have very
clear boundaries between modules, if you
have well-defined interfaces that are
not allowed to change, for example.
And
and I would say that brings us to
another
type of guardrail which are
architectural constraints. So, a lot of
languages, they have architectural unit
tests.
Um
they're like unit tests, they execute
extremely quickly. They only look at,
you know, what dependencies exist
between different modules of your code
base.
So, they can analyze it very quickly and
you can say, okay, prevent um
let's say the the um
let's say what could you say the the
uh
the UI from accessing the database
directly. You could say enforce that it
always has to go through the business
logic layer or something like that.
>> Mhm.
>> And because they also tend to make these
weird interconnection between modules
that
a human would never do.
Um if you just let the I sign your
system and then draw your plot of your
system diagram, you will see the
weirdest things that enrage you
or that you encode them into um
additional architecture unit tests.
Yeah. Which I would count as a another
form of guardrail.
>> Is there anything that you would say,
well, this is then still kind of part of
the human responsibility that would not
fit in automated guardrails?
>> Yes. Um so,
something
I mean, if you look at software
engineering and going back to the
traditional way of doing it,
it always used to be, okay, what do we
want to build? How do we build it? How
do we keep it maintainable? Right? Um
keeping the code base clean and simple
means we can go fast for a long time.
And how do we do it? Well, with
architecture, right? We define the
architecture up front and then we start
diving into the modules. How do we
implement each other? I think that
should still stay the same.
Um the models are not there yet where
they can do that on their own.
>> [clears throat]
>> And um my workflow now includes first
understanding exactly what I want to
build, exactly,
uh so that there's no doubt.
And then sketching out how this might
look as a software system.
Right? Could be different services
talking to each other. It could be on a
service level, you know, different
modules talking to each other. Um which
functions do I need in the modules? So,
you specify pretty much entire
architecture except the implementation.
>> [clears throat]
>> And once you have that, you can already
encode that as rules.
You know?
So, this I think that's extremely
important to
um also to combat um
I think on your show um
people already talked about um the
cognitive uh dissonance
um that comes from not reviewing code
where you don't understand your code
base anymore and you're not able as a
human to reason about your code base
anymore. That comes when you don't
understand the architecture anymore and
how components talk to each other within
your software system.
And yeah, you need to do everything to
combat that as much as possible. Yeah.
Um but
yeah.
>> It's very hard for me to imagine where
this is going to go because
I agree with you. If I understand my
software system, I feel like that's the
skill that's really going to remain for
engineers specifically. And I do believe
that the implementation we're already
automating and I feel like with enough
guardrails, we can hone code reviewing
to where only the essence, potentially
the behavior, I see people reviewing
specifications. That will then also
remain. But if I put myself in the seat
of an engineer, maybe someone that's
listening who's in a bigger
organization, you might not already know
your system,
then it's quite difficult to be like,
okay, this piece of the puzzle in
advance, do I really know how to build
it or how much investigation do I need
to do? That's all work that would happen
up front now. And potentially before AI,
you would do that kind of as you go and
you would iterate and you would improve.
That whole way of working is now
different.
>> Yeah, um
it's very very very difficult to be
messy in your approach now, which is
also why people find it what I would say
why some people might resist it because,
you know, doing all the hard work up
front,
right? You're not uh just discovering as
you just said as you go. You're doing
all the hard work up front. Um
you probably have to do a couple of
iterations on your on what your
implementation to get a better idea of
how good actually looks like.
>> Mhm.
>> So, that's not uncommon, but you can do
that with wipe coding.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
And um
I think that is uh that is going to be
the new normal for for for some time to
come before things change again.
The
But the interesting part is that,
you know, I always ask people, well, how
could you develop software if you didn't
know what you wanted to build?
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
That's also not possible. So, you're
doing the same work now. It's just that
um you're doing it up front, right?
Which might feel more intense, more
involved. But that also means that this
is becoming its own discipline.
And uh when people think about, you
know, what should junior engineers do
now that AI can generate all the code,
um I would say, well,
this is clearly something that can
learn. That's an acquirable skill.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
>> I've seen the best software engineers
kind of fall into two categories. The
ones where, like you mentioned,
someone had to build something and I saw
them stare at their screen. This was
still before COVID where we I worked at
the office 5 days a week. And I saw them
with kind of pencil and paper, and he
was like
writing stuff and drawing things out
before even doing any hands-on.
>> Yeah.
>> And I was like, that's a very
interesting skill. And then I saw other
people where they're like, it's very
hard for me to imagine, and I have to
start typing. But then they're still
fascinating and extremely effective in
the way they operate, but it's
completely like
the inverse of what the first engineer
would do.
>> Absolutely. And the cool thing is that
if you allow yourself to do that, like
to do the prototyping, to go into this
discovery before you put your
specifications not into stone, but
before you kind of say, "Okay, this is
what we want to build."
>> Mhm.
>> Um is that it's all incredibly
rewarding.
I really enjoy that.
Um because um you we really feel the
speed that AI gives you when you iterate
through ideas.
Um I oftentimes find myself talking to
an AI for an hour just to explore this
idea and then maybe a tangent idea and
uh that maybe I shouldn't have gone on,
but um
it teaches you so much about how you can
think about systems.
>> Mhm.
>> And it also elevates you as an engineer
because now you're not only thinking
about, "Okay, how do I implement this?"
but you also think about what do we
actually need?
Right? What does the customer need? So,
the
um
you you can see that
I think engineers get much more
elevated. They start to think at that
product level much more now.
>> Mhm.
>> Um because of that. And that's just
[clears throat] going to continue versus
before they would think about, "Okay,
but how do we write this in code?"
>> How's it been for you? Because uh a lot
of engineers I talk to when they
parallelize work
is there's a lot of stuff going up here
in terms of thinking and execution power
all of a sudden. And at the end of the
day, they're exhausted.
>> Yeah. Um well, the burnout because
you're constantly um exposed to stimuli
and you're constantly context switching
because the AI takes 20 minutes to
respond to you, that's real. That's
absolutely real.
Uh talked to a developer last week and
said on Wednesday his brain out. He just
He's just His brain is
uh on standby because he's constantly
reacting all the time.
Um I think that's 100% real.
>> Mhm.
>> As with anything, I think the way to
combat that is A, discipline. Well,
okay, the first step is to You have to
be aware of what you're doing.
Um
but you also learn how to interleave
tasks, maybe on the same project that do
different things.
Right? So, the work on on uh the
environment that guides the agent,
that's its own project. Besides the
actual pro- project that you're trying
to build.
So,
and I keep iterating between the two.
So, when I'm waiting for an agent to
complete something, uh because I want to
see what it what it does or how it did
it,
um I will just switch to something else.
I might start another session with a
different agent on the same code base
and start interrogating the agent about
the code base.
And so, I stay kind of in the same
context,
>> Mhm.
>> but I don't switch between project as
hard.
>> Yeah.
>> And uh if I don't do that, what ends up
happening is that I keep have to type in
the session, "Uh please tell me what did
we do in the last half hour?" So, I just
It has to remind me of what I did and um
it's weird sometimes. 100% Yeah.
>> Yeah, I saw Claude Code does that
automatically now. If you're out of a
session for too long, it gives you like
a summary of what you've done. So, you
don't [laughter] have to ask anymore.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, there might be some UX problem
they're solving. The
I I think ownership, and we already
mentioned cognitive debt, is going to be
a very crucial topic that distinguishes
kind of engineers that
don't really maybe care about this craft
or about their work. And also, I I spoke
with Addy Osmani last week and he
mentioned this newsroom which which I
hadn't heard of, which he he mentions
cognitive surrender, where people are
like
the agent just takes the wheel, and if
it's the problem, it's the agent's
fault, and if it works, it's also the
agent, but well, then it's a little bit
me, but they really just let go of what
they are responsible for. And I feel
like that's quite risky in the way we
are evolving. I think conversations like
you and I are having are incredibly
important to give people perspective
and to also challenge what goes away and
what remains as part of your
accountability.
>> Absolutely. And
the funny [clears throat] thing is
basically what employees are doing is
they they give people a hand grenade,
which is AI, and then say don't blow up
the hand grenade, but use it, right?
So there's a lot of risk with AI, but
all of that is going to be standardized.
They're going to be policies on what you
are allowed to do and what not with AI.
And uh
the the example I gave with Amazon,
right? They already made a policy
distinction between your code that is
more critical than other code and how
that should be reviewed. So we're just
going to see the same thing and just
going to be another um
I guess form of the part of the process
for software engineers, right? Where
um
you have to define stuff where if you
just want to yolo it, okay, let's not
touch the billing system, please.
Um I think that's going to be
normal pretty soon.
And um yeah, and also um a lot of the
review work that we don't want to do as
humans we can outsource to AI as well.
So
the the idea of not doing any code
reviews comes I mean it's kind of like a
loaded idea, right? Uh but
when you attempt to do that, there there
are a lot of realizations come with it,
right?
They're cheap wins like guardrails. Um
right? They are deterministic, they
execute cheaply and quickly.
>> [snorts]
>> And then
the conversation shifts towards
architecture and specifications and more
validating the specifications up front
than you know than the code later.
And
likewise, even when you have to review
the architecture later as a human, you
can still use AI for that, right? You
have a conversation with the AI. Maybe
you have a specialized agent um
that you particularly set up to review
for any violations of a specific type of
um
architecture that you're trying to
implement in your project. So, you can
also um do an automatic scan over all of
your changes, code changes with AI.
And then use that as the point to start
looking into it as a human.
>> Mhm.
>> [clears throat]
>> Right? So,
um
you can still automate a lot and it's
really just about
okay, where should I look? Where where
don't I have to look?
>> Yeah.
>> Um otherwise, I don't see how
how we're going to scale the review
part, you know? Um
if code generation is 10 times faster,
100 times faster, the pressure's going
to be on all of the systems that come
downstream from that.
>> Absolutely.
>> And part of that is the review with the
human in the loop. So, we have to try to
minimize that as much as we can.
>> Yeah. The I feel like the input we can
likely scale faster, right? We can just
execute on more ideas and validate
things in production with different
tests. The reviewing process is really
the challenge. And some of the things
that you mentioned, I do see those as
ingredients to kind of solving this
puzzle that is the code reviewing
process and not having a human in the
loop at all. If that's the let's say the
big goal that we're working towards,
even though it might not be feasible now
with the models we have, I do see
guardrails in there. I do see capturing
as much as you can behavior and
functionality in tests. I don't think
there should be any reason to not write
a test anymore because you can just
generate the test according to the
behavior that you want. Right? If you
solve a bug, definitely make a test out
of that. That was already good practice,
but there's no reason to not do that
anymore nowadays.
>> Yeah, that's the trend.
>> Yes, and
what also people don't what people also
often forget is that generating a test,
a small piece of code, the chances of
the LLM not doing it right are much
smaller than when you tell the LLM
generate me microservice.
>> Yeah.
>> Right? So, that's also another point um
that I think helps when you uh write
guardrails because if even if you
generate them automatically, which is
what I do, um the chances of failure are
relatively slim.
>> Mhm. I have seen and spoken to other
teams. I'm trying to get one on the
podcast that have fully adopted Spectra
in development as part of their
workflow. They use one of the
specification frameworks and they're
very happy with their approach. That's
why I want to have them on the podcast.
But they mentioned that they have not
built
I think, it's my assumption, got the
guardrails like you and I are discussing
within their code review process. What
they have done
is their review process now very much
revolves around the specification and
that is what reviewed. That is what is
reviewed and I do think they have some
guardrails in place to make sure that
whatever's in the specification is also
translated in code in a certain way.
For me, there's only kind of the the
risky part which is the
non-deterministic behavior that can be
in there.
But I think that's an interesting
approach.
>> Yes, and actually good that you
mentioned that because guardrails can
also mean just a prompt, right? Um
that's I think how guardrails, you know,
started to be defined if I'm not
mistaken. But they can be deterministic
as well. The specification driven
development approach, I really like
that, but mostly because it gives a
human clarity of what is being built.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
if you give that to an LLM and you
observe what it does, you'll be
surprised that after 5 minutes already
starts to deviate from your intentions.
>> Mhm.
>> Because you didn't specify something
clear enough or it there was some room
for interpretation anywhere. So, you can
iterate now on your specification trying
to get it um perfect.
Then you switch the model and it doesn't
work anymore.
>> Mhm. So, does this mean from your
perspective, what do you think of
Spectra and development? Is it something
that works now, but it's going to go
foregone in the future or how do you see
that?
>> Well, I think that is part of um
the discovery product process of what
we're trying to build.
And I think it's I'm trying extreme
important to have that.
>> Mhm.
>> Um because that can also be used for
automated test later, like checking. Do
we Did we actually do this? How did we
do this?
Did we do this in accordance to our
coding principles?
Right? Those are questions you can then
give to an AI to investigate. So, the
specs will stay there. Um people like to
go uh in depth with the specifications,
like they treat it as if it was code.
It's not.
>> [clears throat]
>> All right? It's just um a document of
shared understanding, I would say, that
specifies
um
you know,
part of the behavior, part of what what
is being built.
I think a fine-grained behavioral
specification of whatever you're
building is much more important.
Um
there was this idea of uh TDD, where if
you have um
uh all of your tests and your software
gets deleted, but you still have your
tests, you can rebuild your software.
That was one of the ideas of TDD.
Um
and
well, I have seen it work for the very
first time when I had behavioral tests
implemented that would give the agent
feedback.
And I had a specification as a prompt to
start the implementation.
That was the very first time in my life
I had seen this actually work uh in my
in my project. That's still quite
incredible. I wonder if with existing
code bases,
right, if the test coverage, in theory,
a lot of this is in theory, which is why
why it's quite the challenge, but I
wonder if indeed, if you would throw out
the code, if people have been doing TDD
in that code base for quite a while, if
an AI indeed can then generate the code
exactly how it is according to the
behavior that was captured.
>> Yeah, well, if you have some tokens to
burn, you can try that over the weekend.
>> [laughter]
>> That seems like an interesting
experiment.
What I have noticed is that
also the bigger companies, previously,
before AI and agentic software
engineering,
I feel like they were trailblazing and a
lot of smaller organizations were
looking up to good practices, best
practices, conventions, and blog posts
of what is out there and what's
happening. Right now, I feel like the
playing field is quite equal because
everything is very quickly evolving. You
already mentioned uh over a few months,
harnesses and their capabilities might
change and what is effective and all of
a sudden what is now possible,
which gives us a very interesting
playing field to experiment with. How do
you typically experiment and educate
yourself?
>> Yeah, it's a constant trying to catch up
feeling behind
type of thing.
Um, but I think that's normal for
everybody who's trying to keep up with
things.
So, I like to use projects. Um, I have a
couple of different projects that are on
a different scale of one project that is
purely by coded, purely. Never looked at
the code. I've only prompted it to do
stuff.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh, I have one project that is a CLI
project that is that's the one that I
use for the
TDD approach with the behavioral
specification behavioral tests as guide
rails.
Um,
where I test that type of approach.
I have another project that consists of
multiple microservices, which is much
more complex, which is mostly specs
specs driven.
>> Mhm.
>> And I keep adding features to them using
these different methodologies that I set
up for this project and just observe
what does the AI do, what does it do
wrong, etc.
And more often than not, I see the AI do
something weird.
And then make I make that immediately
part of my
a default guide rails.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, so I kind of have a repository where
I have a default project setups for
different languages and they're
preloaded with a certain type of guide
rails that I found useful in the project
that I do. So, the experimentation
involves a lot of communicating with the
LLM.
Um,
I really found it useful to ask the LLM
to explain itself. So, if if I I give it
a complex task, typically what I ask is
please tell me what your understanding
is of what we are trying to do.
Very simple question. So, I'm trying to
find out what the model understood what
I said versus what I said. And you can
see how models interpret things
differently.
And that gives you an idea of you know,
like personality is too far reach, but
it's sort of type, you know, what type
of
personality does this model exhibit?
Like what type of behavior does it
exhibit? Probably the better
uh term to use, yeah.
So, I do that a lot. Um
Also try out the latest tools that they
give us. Like when sub agents came, I
tried that out.
Um I concluded that I have zero
visibility about what the agents are
doing. Like what are they communicating
with? I have no introspection.
>> Mhm.
>> So, then what I would do is I try to
have introspection to that and I built
my own
kind of system where I just told an
agent, "Please spawn a sub agent, but do
it in a different terminal so I can
actually see what you send to that
different agent."
And yeah, well.
You will see the weirdest things that
the models tell each other, right? You
can already see how the models start to
deviate like at the first uh step when
they hand off tasks, et cetera.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
So, trying to look under the hood as
much as possible, what information gets
exchanged, um monitoring what the agents
do when they talk to each other, I think
those are incredibly important things
for the orchestration itself.
And
I learn a lot uh the most from looking
at those types of um
things, of what the models do and how
they talk to each other. So, I I think
that is how
I experience most of the time to refine
my understanding of what the models do
and also trying to apply, you know, what
they give us in terms of tools.
>> Mhm.
If someone's listening and they want to
apply agentic software engineering to
their own way of work, way of working,
some piece of code that is already live
in production and likely the team has
already adopted some practices or not at
all and they want to kickstart
something. What is step one that you
would recommend?
>> For an individual developer or for
somebody in a team?
>> They could be within a team. I think
that's the most
uh profound case.
>> Uh I would say the simplest thing is
start with guardrails, um
static checks,
>> Mhm.
>> right? You should have, of course, a
code formatter, you should have a
Um
try to write some Semgrep rules that
enforce some of the best practices that
you see in your codebase.
You can ask the AI, for example,
"What are some anti-patterns that we use
in the codebase?" Write a simple test
that flags them.
Um if you work in a team, have a team
discussion, you know.
Um if you get resistance, well, then try
the next next best thing. It's really
difficult to convert people who are not
um buying into the ideas of trying to
improve the codebase by stream-lining it
with tests or with guide rails.
>> Mhm.
>> But um you can run all of these things
on your local machine. You don't have to
enforce everybody to use it, but you can
use it for all code that you write
yourself.
You know, you compare that with a smart
script that checks whether you created
that file or somebody else.
>> Mhm.
>> And um where you enforce your guide rail
rules.
Um
and
the key point is you should measure
or at least get an impression of how it
works with
those guide rails that you put in place
versus without them.
Um because once you see that
they actually help you do more work and
be less in the loop, uh you will not go
back, I don't think.
>> [laughter]
>> It's it's
>> Yeah.
>> It's becomes really convenient to not
have to worry about that and to babysit
the model all the time.
>> I I can see that, right? This term
babysitting I'm trying to get rid of in
the conversations that I have with
people and I'm trying to figure out what
the best way is.
It could be indeed kind of experimenting
and going into this cycle of continuous
improvement and it could be you
capturing behavior as you want as guide
rails for the agent to then pick up and
do something with. And it can also be
feedback that you get from your team,
right? If you and your agent create a
pull request and then there's feedback
from your team, you can also then
capture that in more guide rails.
>> And that's also another idea. So, what
you can do is you can just ask the AI,
"Hey, analyze my session logs on this
project."
It'll go into your uh home folder .cloud
and will start looking at all of your
conversations, and you can ask it, "Do
you see any
um patterns where I had to repeatedly
remind you of a certain thing?" Mhm. So,
you can data mine your session logs to
see where the model goes wrong, where
you always have to correct it. Turn that
into a static check.
Right?
>> This feels like a product that I would
want to have.
>> Yeah.
>> Which is actually not a bad idea.
>> well, actually it's it's a skill. You
can just uh
well, use a skill builder, tell it to
write you that skill. It's very easy. It
takes like 15 minutes, and then you can
use it.
>> Absolutely. Earlier we mentioned
different harnesses might have different
results.
>> Yeah.
>> And in some organizations, some people
just get one harness, and that's it,
right? We've gone all in on GitHub
Copilot cuz it has all the models, you
know, but it's only one harness.
What would you recommend to either those
people or those organizations?
>> That's a really difficult one. If you
can choose your tools as a developer,
uh I don't think any developer is really
going to be happy with that.
Um
I think education would help in that
case.
You know, um I mean, there studies out
there that compare harnesses. Um we have
enough added evidence to suggest that
relying on one particular uh tool um is
not going to keep us at the edge.
So, there are lots of arguments to be
made.
I understand that organization
have this this this this desire tendency
just to standardize things, but it's not
like you select a product and then you
run with it for 5 years. That's not how
AI works.
>> Mhm.
>> And um that just needs understanding of
what AI actually means.
>> Yeah. I feel like that's then missing,
right? Because the we are now beyond
models specifically, and the harness
might matter more than the models
itself.
>> Yes.
>> On paper, I think it's easy to
understand models because that's we've
been talking about that for a long, long
time, right? It's been 2 3 years right
now.
>> Yes.
>> We've gone continuous iterations of
models, and now I feel like more so this
year, maybe even end of last year, the
conversation about harnesses really
started arising.
>> Yes. Well, there's another thing you can
do as a solo developer. Try to find out
at what things you particular harness is
good at.
>> Mhm.
>> Maybe it's it is at um you know, writing
pull requests, documentation.
Maybe it's really good at debugging. So,
try to find those uh use cases where you
can still use it and
then you use it for that.
>> Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. For the people
listening, I'm trying to do this new
thing because I want your advice on what
experiment you want people to run if
they have a week time and they can do
one experiment as kind of their budget
of time they have. What would you want
them to do an experiment with?
>> Well, that depends on where you are in
the organization, I would say. But, for
developers,
I mean, there are a couple of options
and it depends on what you want.
Do you want to get better at agentic
engineering, like working with AI?
Do you want to get better at building
your guardrails? Do you want to get
better at understanding how the models
behave?
So, that that's the first question,
right? What what do you want? There's an
infinite many different options of what
to do. Um I would recommend
if you want to get started with
guardrails,
start looking at semantic grep. Let's
try to encode some of your human
feedback that you would give in a PR
as a rule.
And the the example that I gave earlier
with no default values in method
parameters, that could be one example.
Another one could be um
okay, let's never swallow any errors.
That was any error must always be
propagated.
Something like that.
Um just start with experimenting with
that
and see how um
you your agent
uh reacts in that environment.
>> Mhm.
>> So, um setting up I think the guardrails
so that you can start to improve them
and iterate on them, I think that's very
worthwhile and you will see I would
argue that you would see wins very
quickly
even though you might as well think
yeah, but we had the static code checks
first. But, now you're doing it in a way
that you encode your human preference as
rules.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> custom for your particular project.
>> Florian, thanks so much for coming on.
>> Well, thanks for having me.
>> This is really good.
>> Thank you.
>> If you're still with us, let me know in
the comment section what you thought of
this episode, and we'll see you in the
next one.